[Music]
welcome to this presentation on the
application of the free energy principle
to estimation and control my name is
Hank ramesh nama Chalmers University of
Technology this is joint work with test
from the lag from tu and Hoeven and our
cha or Chile Cali from Uppsala
University the motivation for this work
lies in the area of stochastic optimal
control the picture on the right shows
an agent which can act on its
environment in first the state of the
environment through sensors and
observations and collects rewards using
a control theoretical tation we have the
following ingredients the state X which
can contain the state of the agent and
the world the control or action u the
observations Y and finally the goals a
classic example is LQG which stands for
linear quadratic Gaussian control here
the agent has linear dynamics and a
quadratic cost quadratic in both the
state and the control LQG features a so
called separation principle where the
control assumes a point estimate of the
state and ignores any uncertainty of the
state and on the other hand the
inference is done by a common filter
which assumes known past controls this
decouples the control and inference
problem in more general context
inference can be solved through the
belief propagation algorithm of which
the Kalman filter is a specific instance
in addition to this classic example
there exist more modern approaches such
as model predictive control and
reinforcement learning a model
predictive control we assume to have
knowledge of a generative model of the
agent dynamics as well as the
observation model the goals are encoded
with a loss or objective function and
based on this the model predictive
controller solves an optimization
problem to determine the current control
action on the other hand reinforcement
learning typically is model-free so it
does not have a generative model and it
builds value functions or policies the
goals of the agent are recorded via a
reward signal in this work we will use a
third way called active inference based
on the reference below roughly speaking
active inference tries to minimize free
energy or entropy or taking the quote
from this paper it acts to minimize
surprise
avoiding surprise is a fundamental for
survival and speaks to the basic need of
organisms to maintain equilibrium with
their environment
the main question that we all want to
answer in this work is the following can
we express stochastic optimal control in
general and al QG control specifically
as special cases of active inference
where this motivation in mind this
brings me to the outline of this
presentation first I will provide some
brief background on LQG and belief
propagation then I will elaborate on
different ways how a belief propagation
has been used for control problems then
we move on to the main topic which is
the use of active inference for control
and a relation to LQG I will then show
one example result and wrap up with
conclusions so let's first start with
lqg and belief propagation let us start
with LQG linear quadratic Gaussian
control I have taken this information on
this slide from Wikipedia the first box
shows the evolution of the state as well
as the observation model the state at M
I plus 1 is a linear function of the
state at time I and the control perturb
by Gaussian noise the observation at
time I is a linear function of the state
at time I plus independent Gaussian
noise so this is the linear part of the
LQG the quadratic part refers to the
cost the cost to be minimized is a
quadratic function in the state and in
the control there's an expectation over
all
random variables so basically we want
our agent to stay close to zero and do
this with as low control as possible it
turns out that this system can be solved
in closed form and the discrete time LQG
controller is given by these equations
the first equation gives us the
evolution of the state given the control
and this is basically the equation from
the Kalman filter the estimate of the
state at time I so here the Hat refers
to an estimate depends on the previous
estimate the control and a correction
factor which depends on the current
observation give it an estimate of the
state we can then find a control by a
linear feedback so we have a linear
function depends on the state estimate
now in these expressions there are
several matrices and this can be found
from the so called riccati equations
solving the riccati equations provides
the matrices needed to find the
discrete-time LQG controller the figure
on the right visualizes the LQG
controller so we have a Kalman filter
which takes into account this control
input the observation generates a state
estimate then there's a multiplication
with minus K which yields do control the
control is applied to the plant or the
system and then this generates via a
sensor and new observation which again
is fed to the Kalman filter we now move
on to belief propagation in belief
propagation we consider distributions
over multiple variables such as here P
of x1 x2 and x3 we assume that this
distribution can be factorized as
follows so there's a normalization
constant 1 over Z and then 3 factors F a
FB and FC where each factor contains a
subset of the arguments of the original
distribution from this factorization we
can draw a factor graph in this factor
graph each vertex for each node
correspond
to a factor and each edge or line
corresponds to a variable so for
instance a corresponds to FA X 1
corresponds to the variable X 1 we see
that a only connects to X 1 so this
means that FA has only one variable
namely X 1 but X 1 connects to a and B
this is because X 1 appears in FA and FB
what's this factor graph we can run the
belief propagation algorithm this is a
message passing algorithm over the
factor graph the messages we pass are
functions of The Associated variables so
again we here have the factor graph and
it will now pass messages from this from
the edges of the fact graph in word so
we first compute a message from a to X 1
which we denote by mu from FA to X 1
evaluate it and the value X 1 and this
message or this function is just given
by the original function FA of X 1 at
the same time we can compute a message
from X 3 to see some you from X 3 to FC
evaluated in the value X 3 I will just
set this to 1 now given these two
messages we can compute messages from FB
to X 2 and FC to X 2 both are functions
of the variable X 2 the message from FB
2 X 2 evaluated the value X 2 is given
by the function FB multiplied by the
incoming messages so that's the message
from a to X 1 and then we integrate out
all the variables except X 2 similarly
the message from FC to X 2 is the
function FC which depends on X 2 and X 3
multiplied by the incoming message which
we've computed in the previous time step
and that we integrate out over
everything except X 3 finally we can
compute these messages from FB to X 1
and from FC 2 X 3 following the same
rules
after this third time step on each edge
we have two messages one from left to
right and one from right to left
given these messages we can compute
so-called beliefs the belief of x1 the
belief of x2 and the belief of x3 and
these are simply the marginals of the
original distribution so pfx 1 is
obtained by taking the original
distribution and integrating out
everything except x1 and this belief
which is equal to the marginal is given
by the product of the two messages the
message from left to right from a 2x1
and a message from right to left from B
to x1 the same holds for x2 and x3 and
this provides a systematic and efficient
way to infer hidden variables it can be
shown that these beliefs are exact when
the graph has no cycles when the factor
graph has cycles or loops the beliefs
are only approximations belief
propagation has many applications
including the Kalman filter the particle
filter decoding of error correcting
codes and image processing to name but a
few
we now focus on the relation between
belief propagation and free energy
minimization because an active inference
we also minimize the type of free energy
to reveal this connection let's express
the Joint Distribution P of X in a
slightly different way so here X refers
to the vector of all the variables so X
can be a very high dimensional variable
we write P of X as 1 over Z and Z is a
normalization constant and then a
product over functions so product a over
possibly many functions FA where each FA
takes as argument XA where XA is a
subset of the original X we now
introduce a new notation Y of X defined
as the sum of the logarithm of the
individual FAs with this new notation Y
of X we can express P of X as 1 over Z
times the exponential of minus G of X
here Y of X can be interpreted as a kind
of energy so U of X tells us
energy of a certain configuration X the
distribution P of X will have most of
its mass in low-energy configurations
hence and free energy minimization the
normalization constant Z can in
principle be found by solving this
integral ok now with this in mind let us
now try to formulate a new optimization
problem so we want to minimize with
respect to Q so here Q is the set of
distributions the divergence between Q
and P and P is the original distribution
block plugging in the definition of the
Kubik library divergence we can express
the divergence as an expected energy
Mises - an entropy minus log of Z so the
cool buck libor divergence has an
average energy and entropy and then
finally log of Z which is called a lock
partition function the first two terms
are called the beta free energy since we
want to minimize the divergence we try
to find a Q that minimizes the average
free energy the average energy and at
the same time has high entropy so it's
as broad as possible
while minimizing the average energy now
this is an optimization problem so we
can in principle for formulates at the
Lagrangian and solve this optimization
problem and it turns out and this was
shown in reference to that solving for Q
of X given some structure on Q of X
leads to the belief propagation message
passing rules so this has this
consequence that's when you're doing
belief propagation you're actually
solving a better free energy
minimization problem namely this one
with this background in mind we cannot
move on to the relation between belief
propagation and control let us assume
that we have a generative model and we
want to infer hidden States so what we
can do is we can determine the Joint
Distribution of the States and the
observations given the controls
due to the Markov assumption this
distribution factor Isis as the prior
times the dynamic model and the
observation likelihood let's further
assume that our control objective is
quadratic in the state and quadratic
indoor control now at time T our factor
graph will look something like this we
have a part of the factor graph that
relates to the past where we have the
past controls which are known because
we've already decided them and also the
observations up to time T which are also
known because our sensor has observed
them and then we have the future so this
here contrails contains the future
controls which we do not know and the
future observations which have not been
observed yet the factor graph late to
the past contains the states up to time
T the factor graph of the future
contains the states from time T onward
what connects them here is the state at
time T now on the factor graph related
to the past the one in green we can run
belief propagation and based on this
belief propagation we can find marginals
or beliefs and these are of the form for
instance of the distribution of the
state at some time T prior to the
current time T and including time T
given the observations up to time T and
all the past controls this can be found
by just simply running belief
propagation on this left side so to be a
little bit more specific in the past we
have messages with known controls and
known observations so here are some
arrows that represent these messages and
let us focus on some of these at time T
so the message here labeled a turns out
to be the prediction so this is the
distribution of the state at time T
given the observations in the past so
before time T and also the past controls
so this is what we know about the state
at time T before observing the
measurement YT the message B is the
likelihood so
depends on the observation and then a
message see which connects the past in
the future is the update so this is the
distribution of this data time T given
all the measurements including YT and
the past controls and this update of
course following the message passing
rules is the product the likelihood
function and the prediction and these
messages may seem very familiar to you
because they are just the standard
equations used in the Kalman filter and
the particle filter particle filter now
for the future even though we have this
factor graph it is meaningless to do
belief propagation the reason is that a
control objective C T is not encoded
anywhere in this factor graph so there's
no way to determine reasonable controls
the way this problem has been addressed
in the literature is by encoding the
control objective directly in the factor
graph so here again is our control stage
cost which is quadratic in the states
and quadratic in the control so what
paper number one proposes is to create
an artificial prior on future controls
and this prior is proportional to an
exponential negative the control cost so
what this means for instance when H is
very large is that our generative model
tells us that we will end up in states
with low control similarly to deal with
stage costs related to the state we
introduce artificial known observations
and an associated likelihood function
which is proportional to exponential
negative state cost
so again when R is very large this tells
us that our generative model brings us
to states where X is small we also
remove future observations because those
are not known this then brings us to the
following factorization of the states
from time 0 to time capital T
observations up to time little T because
future observations are removed the
controls from time 1 to time capital T
and then the artificial future
observations from time T plus 1
come time capital T we express this
using the standard Markov model as a
partner to the past with the prior the
state dynamics and the observation model
and then a part related to the pewte to
the future where we again have the stage
state dynamics we have the prior over
future controls and the likelihood
function related to future States here
we show again the factor graph from the
previous slide where the green part
relates to the past the red part relates
to the future and X of T Co connects the
past with the future recall again in
this graph the future controls and the
future observations are unknown we now
replace this part of the future with
this factor graph on the right
corresponding to the factorization above
so what we did is for each control we
added a prior on the control of the form
described above for each state in the
future we add a likelihood function with
an Associated artificial observation
equal to one now we also removed all the
future observations YT so now X and u
are unknown and Z is known but this is
sufficient for us to run the belief
propagation algorithm so we can do for
message-passing where we start from the
updated belief of XT given all
observations up to time little T and all
controls up to time t minus 1 we pass
messages to the future we pass messages
from the future to the current time UT
now we have two messages on this edge UT
and we can compute the belief so
following the belief propagation rule
the belief UT provides us the belief
over the next control action we can take
the mode of this belief and implement
that action and then go through the
entire process again now it was shown
that by doing this we find modified
riccati equations for the LQG problem so
when we specialize this scenario above
to the linear state dynamics linear up
servation Milan quadratic control we
find something that's close to LQG but
not quite the similar idea was proposed
in reference to four state dependent
costs it was proposed to add additional
factors in the factor graph related to
the state cost with a regularizer lambda
and this lambda could be tuned to obtain
desired behavior we are now prepared to
discuss the relation between active and
France and Al Kochi recall that an
active inference we're always trying to
minimize free energy and this leads us
to our main idea similar to the previous
papers we will consider the future
controls as hidden and there are states
to be inferred secondly we will merge
the control cost and the free energy
objective different from before but
without any loss of generality we will
use a rolling horizon where at time t
time little T we will have a horizon
from the current time up to capital T
time steps ahead so now we introduce our
notation y underbar are the observations
up to time little T y over bar are the
observations over a horizon of size
capital T so from time T plus 1 to time
T plus capital T similarly the states
under bar X under bar represents the
states up to time little T x over bar
represents the future states you under
bar represents the controls up to time t
minus 1 u over bar represents the future
controls including the control u T that
we want to infer we will then define a
new generative model at time t denoted
by PT this model depends on all the
observations all the hidden states all
the future controls by this condition on
the past controls we factorize this
distribution into three parts a
normalization constant the system model
which was the old generative model from
early on in this presentation in which
everything was conditioned on all of the
controls times a goal prior and his goal
prior depends on the few
sure states the future observations and
the future controls note that some
variables such as X T appear in the goal
prior and in the system model this is
fine because the normalization constant
Z will make sure that the entire wat
distribution is well-defined and
normalized let us look at the shape of
the proposed goal prior similar to the
previous papers we consider to be in
exponential minus lambda times the cost
over the horizon this cost as you may
recall is quadratic in state and in the
control the parameter minus lambda will
create different behaviors if lambda is
very large this means that our goal
prior is very concentrated around zero
zero and the control and zero and the
state if lambda is very small meaning
close to zero this means that the goal
prior is very flat in this state and
control space with this generative model
we can now define a free energy
objective at time T this free energy
objective involves a cool black lab
where divergence where P of T is a
generative model which is given and Q is
a distribution which we would like to
determine by plugging in the definition
of the kullbackleibler divergence as
well as a definition of the generative
model we can break down this free energy
into two parts one part V of T which
depends on the past and one part G of T
which depends on the future the part G
of T also contains the gold priors which
relate to the future we show in the
paper that the first time is minimized
by a common filter and the second term
is minimized by message passing backward
in the factor graph the beliefs can then
be found by running message passing on
the corresponding factor graph with the
gold priors and this beliefs found by
message passing will then also minimize
the free energy objective the principle
outline here is called generalized free
energy there is also a concept called
expected free energy but this is
different and will lead to different
the entire factor graph is shown here in
green again we have the past and right
an orange we have the future and what
connects them is the state at time T the
factor graph corresponding to the past
is exactly the same as it was before and
it is conditioned on all past controls
the fact the factor F has as variables Y
and X under bar so there are the past
observations in the past states the
graph under riot corresponds to the
future we see that there are these
orange vertices in the graph and they
correspond to the factorized gold prior
we call that a gold prior is the
exponential of a sum so this becomes a
product of the Exponential's for each
future state we have a gold prior for
each future control we have a gold prior
we also have gold price for future
observations but these are set to
uniform distributions we can now run
message passing on this factor graph the
messages on the factor graph are
visualized here
oddish focus on some of these messages
the message a from XT going from left to
right is the Kalman filter output after
the update so this is just a standard
common filter running from left to right
the message is B and C regarding future
states they are backward messages in the
factor graph which accounts for future
goals this depends on the gold priors
and future times now the message is e
and D the message e dowered accounts for
the gold prior of the control at time T
and the message D upward accounts bolt
for the output of the Kalman filter a
and the future goals C and B we can then
multiply the messages E and D and this
provides us the belief of the control at
time T which we are interested in we can
uh apply the mode of this belief to the
system and shift our time horizon with
one step and apply the same principle
again the question now arises what can
we prove about the relationship between
active inference as proposed in the
previous slide and LQG in the paper we
prove the following two statements under
a deterministic generative model active
inference solves the stochastic optimal
control problem so here the state
dynamics and the observation model are
fully deterministic secondly even when
the generative model is not
deterministic but lambda becomes very
small but positive then also active
inference solves the underlying
stochastic optimal control problem to
make this specific for LQG we find the
following expressions for the controller
with the gain of the controller as well
as the additional matrices that are also
used in the riccati equations different
from the standard riccati equations we
have lambda and many of these
expressions but again it is possible to
show that when either condition one or
two holds then the lambda cancels out in
all these expressions and we recover
exactly the lqg riccati equations so it
is easy to verify that the under
condition one or two the controller
becomes exactly the lqg controller let
us show some results to verify our
claims this slide shows the performance
of the LQG an active inference
controller for a time window of 10 steps
each of the four figures as on the
x-axis time and under y-axis different
quantities of interest on the bottom
left we have the control magnitude which
we would like to be small we have the
state magnitude which we would also like
to be small on the bottom right we have
the accumulated control cost and on the
top right we have a measure of the free
energy in each of the figures we show
three curves the lqg is in blue in red
is the active inference controller with
lambda equal to one and in green is the
active inference controller with lambda
equal to 0.1 we observe data LQG
controller
flies large controls in the beginning to
bring the magnitude of the state close
to zero and then apply small Corrections
in contrast to active inference
controller with lambda equal to one is
very sluggish and applies only very
small controls needed to slow decrease
of the state magnitude as a function of
time the active inference controller
with a small lambda equal to 0.1 based
very close to the LPG controller this
can also be seen in the bottom right
showing the accumulated cost where lqg
and the active inference with lambda
equal to 0.1 achieve similar accumulated
cost while the active inference
controller with a large lambda leads to
a large accumulated cost so these
results confirm that for small lambda
the active inference Controller recovers
lqg so it is interesting to see that
larger lambda
leads to less aggressive control the
lower free energy with higher cost and
this result is somewhat counterintuitive
one would expect that a larger lambda
would lead to more aggressive control
bringing the state and the control
magnitude close to zero quickly recall
that with a large lambda we will have a
very concentrated goal prior around the
target value of zero the interpretation
of this is as follows if your model
tells you that you will anyway end up
where you want so this means with large
lambda your model tells you that you
will have a control and a state close to
zero then there is no need to work hard
to get there so there is no need to
apply large controls to reach your goal
because you think you will get there
anyway this was a counterintuitive but
interesting result this now leads us
finally to our conclusions active
inference is a flexible and general
framework can be applied to stochastic
control and it has classical LQG as a
special case provided we defined a free
energy objective appropriately active
inference automatically deals for
different kinds of uncertainty including
in the generative model itself the
variational formulation is also good
because it allows us to include various
kind of objectives and constraint
also it does not presume any separation
principle as an algae it naturally
emerges over all active inference is a
rich and emerging area with lots of open
research problems for the control signal
processing and statistics community with
this I would like to thank you for your
time and your attention and your
interest in our research
[Music]